<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The certainty of the future judgment asserted and proved in a sermon preached at St Michael's Crooked Lane, London, Octob. xxvi, 1684 / by Matth. Bryan ...</title>
            <author>Bryan, Matthew, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5246</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19907</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12115906</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12115906</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54305</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29934)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54305)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 760:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The certainty of the future judgment asserted and proved in a sermon preached at St Michael's Crooked Lane, London, Octob. xxvi, 1684 / by Matth. Bryan ...</title>
                  <author>Bryan, Matthew, d. 1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, V, 11 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54305:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CERTAINTY OF THE <hi>
                  <hi>Future Judgment</hi> Aſſerted and Proved,</hi> IN A SERMON PREACHED At S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Michael</hi>'s <hi>Crooked Lane, London,</hi> Octob. xxvi. 1684. By <hi>MATTH. BRYAN,</hi> Lecturer there. <hi>Publiſhed in the Author's Vindication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:54305:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54305:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE AND RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in GOD, PETER Lord BISHOP of <hi>WINTON,</hi> AND PRELATE of the <hi>GARTER,</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Lordſhip having been pleaſed to honour me with a Teſtimonial under your Epiſcopal Seal (beſides a Letter to his Grace my Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi>) of my Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour for about ten Years in your Lordſhips late Dioceſe of <hi>Bath and Wells,</hi> when I remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thence to the Place where I now am; I ſhould juſtly have been condemn'd, had thoſe ſcandalous Reports, which are rais'd concerning me, been true, as the vileſt and moſt ungrateful Wretch living, appearing ſo unworthy of, and contrary to the Character your Lordſhip was pleas'd to give me, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at once a diſobedient Son to your good
<pb facs="tcp:54305:3"/>Lordſhip, (to whom I muſt acknowledge my ſelf to ſtand, in many inſtances, more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly obliged) and a diſloyal Subject to the Beſt of Kings.</p>
            <p>This, my Lord, is the reaſon of my inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing to your Lordſhip's Name the following plain Diſcourſe (calculated for a common Auditory) which I am even forc'd out of pure neceſſity to make publick (and therefore humbly beg that it may ſhelter it ſelf under your Lordſhip's Patronage) to ſtop the mouth of a flying Scandal, which has wounded my Reputation, and that the Truth may appear, and the World be ſatisfied how unjuſtly my Sermon preached at St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s <hi>Crooked Lane, London, Octob.</hi> 26. <hi>ult.</hi> was reflected on, and repreſented as Treaſonable and Seditious, and reproaching the Government and the Courts of Juſtice: A heavy Charge and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation! which, I doubt not, Good Men (when undeceiv'd) will conclude to be falſe, and that I am notwithſtanding a true and Loyal Subject to the King, the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhip's moſt Obedient Son, and Obliged Humble Servant,</hi>Matth. Bryan.</signed>
               <date>Decemb. 10. 1684.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:54305:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>IT is not out of Ambition to appear in print, to lie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Book-ſeller's ſtall, and be pointed at in a crowd, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>—that I publiſh the following plain (but pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical) Diſcourſe, (fitted for a private Auditory in my Courſe of Preaching, and not deſign'd for publick view) but in a juſt Vindication of my ſelf from thoſe Aſperſions and unworthy Calumnies, caſt upon me by ſome of my Auditors, who out of Ignorance, or Prejudice, at leaſt not well underſtanding, or regarding what was ſpoken, together with the Scope, and Coherence, or out of I know not what raſh and prepoſterous Zeal (but not according to Knowledge) hoping perhaps to oblige the Government, (whereas in Truth by ſuch practices they really prejudice it, whilſt they reproach and abuſe its Friends, that are truly loyal, and neither ſpeak, nor act any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it, but for it, and that in a lawful Aſſembly) miſerably repreſented my Sermon with ſo black, and frightful a Face, that I was ſtartled at it my ſelf, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their deformed Dreſs, and ſo unlike my Genuine Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue (there being nothing which I abhor more than Diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, Sedition and Treaſon, which, not only my Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples as a Clergy-man, but my Education too, as a Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Son, do, I thank God, ſufficiently arm me againſt) and therefore took a review of its native Complexion, which I ſhew'd again to my Auditors the Sunday follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the major Part of which, and ſome the moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and eminently loyal Perſons, declared it to be the ſame, (without any material alteration) and altogether unlike the monſtrous ſhape, which ſome had made it to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in. With which, though ſome were ſatisfied, not only my Auditors, but others too, particularly, the Honourable Sir <hi>Richard Lloyd</hi> Knight, Dean of the Arches (to whom a complaint was brought againſt me,
<pb facs="tcp:54305:4"/>which was ſoon after contradicted by the ſame Perſon that brought it, being undeceiv'd by a true account from a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry judicious, loyal Perſon, in the Pariſh of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Michael Crooked-Lane,</hi> who was an Auditor of the ſaid Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) and alſo his Grace my Lord of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who has ſince had a true account of the whole matter: Yet I doubt not but there are many, to whom it hath, or will appear with its ugly Vizard, and its blacker Dreſs (which Ignorance, or Malevolence has put upon it) which will provoke them to abhor and curſe the Child and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent too.</p>
            <p>To prevent which miſchief, and undeceive the impartial and unprejudic'd, I thought it neceſſary to print my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, which how faithfully and exactly done, I appeal to the moſt judicious Auditors, both in the Pariſh of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mary Newington</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> (where this very Sermon, that was ſo carp'd at (but not by one of the Auditors there) was preach'd in the Morning) and in the Pariſh of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Michael Crooked Lane, London</hi> (where it was preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Afternoon) who, I doubt not, will be ready to atteſt (if required) that what is here preſented to the World in Print, is the very ſame, without any material alteration, that was preached in each Pariſh on the <hi>26<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>October</hi> ult. and the <hi>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>November</hi> following, at which times was delivered what was objected againſt, and miſ-repreſented in this Diſcourſe, particularly from <hi>p. 1.</hi> to <hi>p. 18.</hi> which is tranſcrib'd from my Notes, as it was preach'd.</p>
            <p>And whether the whole, or any part of it ſpeaks what my Accuſers did (viz. <hi>that I reproach'd and reflected on the Government, and the Courts of Juſtice, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That there is perſecution in our Courts of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature, and that Men are perſecuted there, and could not have Juſtice done them, and that the Judges did take Bribes,</hi> &amp;c.) let the impartial and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudic'd judge.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:54305:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I preſume the ſubtilleſt Head, and moſt critical Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor cannot pick out one thing that looks like <hi>Treaſon,</hi> or <hi>Sedition,</hi> or <hi>Reflection</hi> on the <hi>Government,</hi> or the <hi>Courts of Judicature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how tender a Man ought to be of, and concern'd for his Reputation, is determin'd not only by that famous Oracle,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.1. Vid. Bp. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, p. 23.</note> the wiſeſt Meer-man on earth (who obſerves that <hi>a good Name is better than precious Oyntment</hi>) but alſo by the great Apostle, who (as Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) makes a Slander caſt upon a Miniſter <hi>(qua talis)</hi> to be at leaſt petty
<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 6.11.</note> Blaſphemy: <hi>(Rom. 3.8.)</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>as we are ſlandered, as we are blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Conſideration was perhaps the reaſon that that worthy and learned Prelate preached and publiſhed a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon (and that in his younger years,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon, ut ſupra</hi> p. 21.37.</note> before he was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd to the Epiſcopal Dignity) in vindication of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from a ſevere and unjuſt Imputation.</p>
            <p>I hope therefore I ſhall not be blam'd, eſpecially by my <hi>Reverend Fathers</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> (whoſe <hi>Innocence,</hi> at this rate, may ſoon be blaſted by the viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent tongues of ſuch Detractors, who take the liberty to comment on our Sermons, and report them in their own words, at leaſt catching at part of a Sentence, or a piece of a Period, not minding the Scope, or Coherence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by 'tis poſſible to make foul work with the faireſt diſcourſe that proceeds from the Pulpit) for endeavouring to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve the credit of my reputation, and ſtop the mouth of a flying Slander, which getting upon the wings of Fame (that ſwift and often lying Meſſenger, as the Poet obſerves,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fama, Malum, quo non aliud velocius ullum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mobilitate viget, vireſque acquirit eundo—)</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> need not be bid to make ſpeed to carry its meſſage through the World. <hi>Report,</hi> ſay they in the Prophet,
<note place="margin">Jer. 20.10.</note> 
               <hi>and we will report.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:54305:5"/>
            <p>And though I need not, I confeſs, (which ſome may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort upon me) stand upon the Punctilioes of Honour, or value my ſelf much on that account, being, perhaps, as little in the eyes of the world, as I deſire to be in mine own; yet were I ten times leſs than I am, rather than tamely ſit down under the black cloud of ſo unjuſt a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, and ſevere an Imputation (neither is it inconſiſtent with Chriſtianity, or the meekneſs of the Dove ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, the crime here inſinuated being not ſtrictly a carnal ſin, as <hi>Drunkenneſs, Adultery,</hi> &amp;c. (the reproach whereof, how unjuſt ſoever, I could more eaſily have born, as my <hi>Saviour</hi> did before me) but <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and <hi>Diabolical,</hi> viz. <hi>to deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties)</hi> which a little warm Breath, and brisk Air would ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily blow off; I had rather (I ſay) die than live, it being determined long ago— <hi>Praeſtat penitus emori, quàm per dedecus vivere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will detain the Reader no longer than to tell him that I thought ſit, for the common good, to publiſh my whole Diſcourſe on this Subject (excepting only the Illuſtrations of ſome Particulars relating to the third Head of Diſcourſe, <hi>p. 20, 21.</hi> which I was forc'd to omit, leſt theſe Papers ſhould ſwell too big, (though no more was ſtrictly neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for my Vindication than from <hi>p. 1.</hi> to <hi>p. 18.</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid) that it might not be imperfect, in which the Argument is weighty (how weak ſoever the management be) and a mighty Perſwaſive to a virtuous and good Life. And if the production of it in the World, though by an <hi>Evil Cauſe,</hi> has any good Effect towards the furthering of any ones Salvation, and the promoting of his ſpiritual and eternal Good, I have my End, who deſire to live no longer in the World, than I may be ſineerely ſerviceable to <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and my <hi>Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54305:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 COR. v. 11. the former Part.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Knowing therefore the terrour of the Lord, we perſwade men—</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle in this and the former Chapter, profeſſeth his Chriſtian integrity with the conſtancy of it, and that upon a double Motive, <hi>viz.</hi> the expectance of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Glory, and the General Judgment. Of the former he ſpeaks in the Cloſe of the fourth Chapter, and the Beginning of this: And as this Motive was before his eye, ſo that of Judgment to come, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>For we muſt all appear before the Judgment-ſeat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his body, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad.</hi> Which laſt Motive, or Argument he lays down by way of Poſition or Doctrine, and in the Words of my Text draws his Inference from it by way of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to others: <hi>Knowing therefore the terrour of the Lord, we perſwade men—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Knowing] i. e.</hi> being aſſured of the certainty of Judgment to come, which he calls <hi>The terrour of the Lord,</hi> being the cauſe of terrour. <hi>We] i. e.</hi> I and the reſt of the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt, do <hi>perſwade men, i. e.</hi> preſs and excite and ſtir up and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54305:6"/>them to their Chriſtian Duties, to Goſpel-Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Obedience.</p>
            <p>So that the Remark or Obſervation, which natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ariſeth from the Words, is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>That the preſſing and perſwading men to Goſpel-Piety and Obedience by the Apostles and Ministers of Christ, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>
               </label> is grounded upon no leſs Motive than the infallible certainty, and ſeverity, and dreadfulneſs of the future Judgment.</q>
            <p>In ſpeaking to which, I ſhall endeavour to do theſe four things:
<list>
                  <item>I. Clear the Point as to its Inference.</item>
                  <item>II. Shew you the infallible certainty of a future Judgment after this Life.</item>
                  <item>III. Enquire into the ſeverity and dreadfulneſs of it, ſtyled here, <hi>The terrour of the Lord;</hi> and then,</item>
                  <item>IV. and Laſtly, Make Improvement of all by Application.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. I ſhall firſt of all endeavour to clear the Point as to its Inference, and ſhew you, That no leſs Motive than this, <hi>viz. The infallible certainty, and ſeverity and dreadfulneſs of the future Judgment,</hi> could put the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt upon the ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt preſſing and perſwading men to Goſpel-Piety and Obedience.</p>
            <p>And this will appear by conſidering what other Motive could have any probability to prevail with them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Could they be prevailed with to tell the World of a <hi>Terrour</hi> that they ſhould never feel, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54305:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>did not believe; and thereupon to preſs Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Piety and Obedience, and that only as an Engine of State-Policy, to keep men in awe, and Obedience to their Governours, and preſerve Civil Peace, as ſome Prophane Men would have it? If ſo, why then were they not more in eſteem with Rulers and Princes, with the Great and Noble? why were they the Mark of their malice and envy, of their rage and fury, if they were hired as their Politick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and did them ſuch great and acceptable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice? Again,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Was it Honour they had in their eye? Why then were they the Object of the World's contempt and ſcorn, ſcoft at, and derided, having <hi>tryal of cruel mockings,</hi> reviled, defamed, and <hi>accounted the filth of the World, and the off-ſcowring of all things?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Was it Profit that was the Motive? Surely no: For then our Saviour, and his Apoſtles, and Miniſters would have had a greater intereſt in the World; then they would have had full Cheſts and Barns to boaſt of, as well as others. But 'tis notorious, how great a degree of poverty did await them: Chriſt himſelf not having a houſe wherein to put his head, no Lands or revenues to give him the title of rich or great. And his Apoſtles following him, left their gainful Trades, and were not much richer than their Maſter. Yea, may it not be truly obſerv'd to this day, that the employment of a Miniſter is none of thoſe direct Courſes to Wealth and Riches? whereas other Arts and Employments can raiſe an Eſtate, and advance a Family, they who wait at the Altar, with their Dependents, for the moſt part live in meaner circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. (Not but that God has a Bleſſing for the Poſterity and Sons of the Clergy, as well as others;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54305:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>many of them arriving to eminent degrees of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Wealth in the World; but then that owes it ſelf not always ſo immediately to their Fathers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and Eſtate in the World, but to their own, through God's Bleſſing upon thoſe Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and gainful Trades wherein they were educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.)</p>
            <p>None of theſe things then could be Motives to the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt to ſet on this Buſineſs: What Motives then could prevail? Would they be ſo mad and indiſcreet to preſs Goſpel-Piety upon the ſuppoſition of a <hi>Terrour</hi> that they ſhould never hear of, or feel, and which themſelves did not believe, and not hope to be advantag'd by it, either here or hereafter? What encouragement were this, nay what madneſs rather, to preſs an idle and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Vertue, an uncommanded Obedience, with deſign only to terrifie and affright the World, and in the mean time expoſe themſelves to diſgrace, and ſhame, and contempt, and reproach, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and perſecution? With what courage or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort could they hold out to preſs this impertinent, unprofitable buſineſs, and that with ſo much ſweat and labour, weakning their Bodies, and waſting their Spirits, endangering their lives and livelihood? If there were no other Motive but this, how ſoon would they have hung the Wing? how ſoon would the Tongue have faulter'd, and been ſilent, and the Spirits faint, and the Hands and Feet have been weary?</p>
            <p>'Tis then certainly no leſs, no more inſeriour Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, than the certain knowledge of the <hi>Terrour of the Lord,</hi> that put them with ſuch earneſtneſs upon this great buſineſs.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:54305:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>'Twas this brought Chriſt from Heaven; <hi>Knowing the Terrour of the Lord,</hi> he came down <hi>to perſwade men; knowing,</hi> I ſay, <hi>the Terrour of the Lord,</hi> the diſpleaſure of the Great God againſt ſin and Sinners, and the certainty of Divine vengeance and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wrath, knowing this, he came into the World to <hi>perſwade men.</hi> This made him with ſo much zeal and earneſtneſs to ſet upon this Buſineſs, to <hi>perſwade men;</hi> and that both by his Doctrine and Miracles, his Life and his Death, by his bitter Paſſion and Sufferings, his Tears and Bloud, his Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, and Miſſion of the Holy Ghoſt; and ſtill continues to perſwade them by his Miniſters and Ambaſſadors, whom he commiſſions and commands to perſwade, and entreat, and beſeech, by all the endearments and compellations of Love, <hi>to flee from the wrath to come,</hi> to be reconcil'd to God, to embrace and improve the means of Grace and Salvation: Which hath tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported their Spirits with zeal and courage, counting nothing dear, but God's Glory and mens Souls; counting, I ſay, nothing dear, neither health, nor ſtrength, nor reputation, nor honour, nor liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, nor their deareſt bloud, which they were content ſhould melt away in the Flames, and be expos'd to the hands of violence, rather than ceaſe to <hi>perſwade men, knowing the Terrour of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this, by the way, may ſerve as an Apology for Miniſters. When you hear them boldly and ſeverely rebuking Vice, and reproving ſin and Sinners, laying open the horrid and abominable nature, and ſad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and conſequents of ſin, and ſo paſſionately and earneſtly perſwading men to repentance, to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Vertue and Holineſs, and that from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of rewards and puniſhments to be diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the other World, and thoſe dreſs'd up in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54305:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>different habit of recommending, or aſtoniſhing, and affrighting circumſtances, proper to each diſtant ſtate: when you hear this, do not cenſure it as a common Lecture of Terrour to awe and affright Children, and the weaker ſort, who are eaſily impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon; as words of courſe, and ſo not much to be regarded; as a Tryal of Skill, and a caſt of our Office; much leſs as a deſign out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and hatred to your perſons to expoſe and abuſe you; which will provoke you to be angry, to ſtorm and rage at the Word, and the Preacher of it. No, but rather look upon it and receive it, as Words ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the deepeſt ſeriouſneſs, and out of true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and charity to your Souls.</p>
            <p>Alas! Sirs! were not ſin ſo dangerous and hurtful to men, were there no future Account to give at the tremendous Audit, were there no ſuch flaming wrath and fiery vengeance as you hear of from the Pulpit, were there no future Rewards for good, and no Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments for bad men, we would never trouble you: For we come upon an unwelcome Meſſage to many, to raviſh their <hi>Dalilahs</hi> out of their Arms, (which may turn their Stomachs, and make them rage, as <hi>Herod</hi> did at <hi>John the Baptist</hi>) to take them off from that which they ſo dearly love, which 'tis as as hard to part with, as to part with a dear Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, with a right Eye, or a right Hand; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſin is compar'd to the Members of the Body: <hi>Mortifie therefore your Members which are upon the earth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>fornication,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And no wonder now that the Sinner ſtorms and grows angry; but we muſt not value that. The Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon would be unfaithful, if he ſhould be loth, or forbear to put his Patient to grief when he ſees his danger: No, he will cut and lance and ſearch the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54305:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Wound, or Sore to the bottom, though he put his Patient to pain, though he cry and lament ſore, and grow angry; he will not ſpare a dear Member, if a Gangrene calls for amputation. The Phyſician will deal plainly with his Patient, and tell him the nature of his Diſeaſe, and his danger, and will make him ſick with bitter Pills, and loathſome Potions, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his Cure. The Lawyer will deal faithfully with his Client, and critically examine, and ſearch into every Creek and Corner of his Evidences, and tell him the worſt, and not flatter him, if he finds any thing defective, that he may conſult a Remedy.</p>
            <p>Now, Sirs! our Work is much like the Work of theſe: like the Chirurgeon we are to cut and lance with the Sword of the Spirit, and the Knife of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, and to ſearch the Sinners Wounds and ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerous Sores to the bottom; yea, and to amputate and diſmember too. Like the Phyſician we muſt tell men of their Sickneſs, and their danger, and doſe them with bitter Pills, and loathſome Potions: We are Phyſicians in Ordinary to the King of Kings, and the World is his great Hoſpital, where do lye abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of impotent Folk, of blind, and lame, and ſick, and diſeaſed, who are our Care; we are bound <hi>ex Officio</hi> to look after them, and muſt deal faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and in ſuch methods as the nature of the Diſeaſe requires. Like the Lawyer, we muſt ſearch and examine our Peoples Evidences for the heavenly Inheritance; yea, like Ambaſſadours, we muſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our Meſſage, whether of Peace, or War. And would you have us flatter and deceive?</p>
            <p>Now were there no need of this, we would not trouble men. But, alas! who can ſee his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's, or his Friend's danger, and not be concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? What an uncharitable man is he, that ſees his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54305:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Neighbour's Houſe on Fire, and will not tell him of it, and endeavour to ſave him from, or pluck him out of the Burnings? that ſees him drowning, and will not help him? that ſees Thieves breaking in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and will not cry out, and aſſiſt him? eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially 'tis the Watchman's Office ſo to do, who will not be loth, or forbear to cry out Fire, at Midnight, or make an Alarm to give notice or Thieves and Robbers, leſt he awake or diſturb the ſecure ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man who is in danger. And, what! ſhall the Watchmen of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who <hi>ex Officio</hi> are bound to give notice of, and help to quench the ſpiritual Flames, hold their peace and be ſilent? Shall we ſee men all in Flames, expos'd to the devouring Fire, the Fire of Luſts burning within them, evidenc'd by the Flames of Vices without, the Flames of wrath and Divine Vengeance over them, and the Flames of Hell underneath them, into which they are ready to drop every moment? Shall we ſee this, and be ſilent, and not cry out and endeavour to quench the Flames, and pluck them out of the Burnings, and ſave them from that conſuming Fire? Shall we ſee them upon the Precipice of deſtruction, juſt falling headlong into ruine, and not ſtretch out a hand to ſave them? Shall we ſee Thieves and Murderers (the Devil and his Agents) breaking in upon Souls, and not give them notice of it, and run to their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance?</p>
            <p>You ought therefore (Brethren!) to put a candid conſtruction on the ſevereſt Lectures from the Pulpit; to take the ſharpeſt Reproofs, the moſt bitter Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives againſt Sin, the moſt earneſt and paſſionate Adjurations, as inſtances of compaſſion, and love to your Souls, and faithfulneſs to him that ſent us. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, 'tis the ſin we hate, while we reprove, but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54305:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet love the Sinner.
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.15.</note> And though ſome perhaps may preach Chriſt <hi>out of envy</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) and others for the ſake of the Bag, with <hi>Judas;</hi> yet, I doubt not, there are many, who have higher Ends and aims, <hi>viz.</hi> God's Glory, and the ſalvation of Souls, who can truly ſay with the Apoſtle here, <hi>Knowing therefore the Terrour of the Lord, we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will ſhut up this with that wholeſome Advice of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>James</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> concerning hearing and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Word preached, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.19, 20, 21. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, my beloved Brethren, let every man be ſwift to hear, ſlow to ſpeak, ſlow to wrath: for the wrath of man worketh not the righteouſneſs of God. Wherefore lay apart all filthineſs, and ſuperfluity of naughtineſs, and receive with meekneſs the ingrafted Word, which is able to ſave your Souls.</hi> To which let me add that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>Wherefore laying aſide all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and all guile, and hypocriſies, and envies, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſpeakings; as new-born Babes deſire the ſincere Milk of the Word, that ye may grow thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here may ſome ſay, If all this is true, that there is a future State, a Day of Judgment coming, ſuch a <hi>Terrour of the Lord</hi> to be reveal'd hereafter, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters do well to be ſo earneſtly and paſſionately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for the Souls of men, to <hi>cry aloud and ſpare not,</hi> to tell them of their Sins, and warn them to <hi>flee from the wrath to come:</hi> but are you ſure you are not under a miſtake, that you do not erre in the Foundation? Are you ſure there is ſuch a future Judgment as you ſpeak of? What evidence or aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance have you of the certainty of it?</p>
            <p>This I ſhall anſwer; and therein, I hope, give you ſatisfaction in the next Particular which I am to ſpeak to, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew you,</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:54305:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="2">II. The infallible certainty of the future Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Now the certainty of a future Judgment af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Death is declar'd and evidenc'd to the World by a threefold voice. <hi>The Voice of Scripture, the Voice of Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>the Voice of God's Justice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Voice of Scripture.</hi> The Jews had a confident Tradition amongſt them, That bleſſed <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch,</hi> who was tranſlated to Heaven, had left two Pillars, as ſacred to Poſterity, wherein were fairly engraven thoſe two great Prophecies, one of the firſt Deſolation of, and Judgment upon the World by water; not many years before which came, God remov'd him, as a Jewel to an heavenly Cabinet, that his eyes might not ſee it. The ſecond Prophecy in a Pillar of Stone, of the Diſſolution of the World by Fire againſt the final Judgment. The latter Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, concerning the final Judgment, is warranted by Scripture, <hi>Jude</hi> 14, 15. <hi>And Enoch alſo, the ſeventh from Adam, propheſied of theſe, ſaying, Behold, the Lord cometh with ten thouſands of his Saints, to execute vengeance upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly among them, of all their ungodly deeds, which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches which ungodly Sinners have ſpoken againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is nothing that the holy Scripture is more plain and poſitive in, than aſſerting a Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Death and Judgment are the Twin-Siſters of the ſame Womb of Decree.
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> 
               <hi>It is appointed unto all men once to dye, and after that the Judgment.</hi> The ſad certainty of Judgment cloſeth up that Iro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Expreſſion of the Wiſe man, or rather a wiſer than He, in reproof of wanton youthful Sinners, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth, and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the ſight of thine
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54305:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>eyes: But know thou, that for all theſe things God will bring thee into Judgment.</hi> Our Saviour does often very poſitively and expreſly mention a Day of Judgment, as we may ſee in all the four Evangeliſts. And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles are often beating upon this Argument. It were endleſs to enumerate Particulars. So poſitive is the Scripture in this Point, that it obſerves to us, that the very Day is appointed, and the Judge na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. <hi>He hath appointed a day in the which he will judge the World in righteouſneſs, by that man whom he hath ordained, whereof he hath given aſſurance unto all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are three Days have an Emphatical Note ſet upon them: the Day of Creation, the Day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and the Day of Judgment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Day of Creation, which <hi>open'd the Door of Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Day of Redemption, which is call'd,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>The Fullneſs of Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Day of Judgment. This ſhall ſhut out Time, and uſher in Eternity. And this Day is Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically call'd <hi>The Day of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.2. Phil. 2.16. Jude 6. Joel 2.31. Eph. 4.30.</note> 
               <hi>the Day of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>the great Day,</hi> and <hi>the great and terrible Day of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>the Day of Vengeance,</hi> and <hi>the Day of Redemption,</hi> and <hi>the Day of refreſhing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That's the firſt Evidence of the certainty of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Judgment, <hi>the Voice of Scripture.</hi> The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is,</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>The Voice of Conſcience;</hi> and that both natural, and enlightned.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Natural Conſcience, which is affrighted at the hearing of a Judgment to come. <hi>Felix</hi> trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at it, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25. <hi>And as he reaſoned of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and temperance and Judgment to come, Felix trembled.</hi> As S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> preached to him of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54305:11"/>and temperance, his guilty Conſcience reflected on all his paſt acts of injuſtice and intemperance; and when he heard of the Grand Audit, the dreadful Judgment, at which he muſt account for all his faults, the mighty <hi>Felix</hi> trembled. 'Twas too harſh a Note, and jarring Sound, and unpleaſant Muſick for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate Ears and accuſing Conſcience to hear, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preſently diſmiſs'd the Preacher, <hi>Go,</hi> get thee gone, ſays he, <hi>for this time, and when I have a more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient ſeaſon, I will call for thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though the Athenians mocked when they heard of the Reſurrection of the dead, yet not at the hearing of the Day of Judgment. The Heathen, by the very Light of Nature, had a ſenſe of Divine wrath and vengeance, which would purſue Sinners. Thus the barbarous People in the Iſland of <hi>Melita,</hi> where S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> arriv'd after his Shipwrack, when they ſaw the Viper leap out of the Fire, and faſten upon his hand, <hi>they ſaid among themſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 28.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>No doubt this man is a Murderer, whom though he had eſcaped the Sea, yet vengeance ſuffereth not to live.</hi> Why, whence had they this Notion of vengeance? Where had this barbarous People theſe Notices? What Goſpel-Preacher ever arriv'd there before, to preach to them this Doctrine of the Divine wrath and vengeance? This Preacher dwelt within them. 'Twas the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Light of God within them, which made diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of the heinous Nature, and Guilt of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the vindicative Juſtice of the inviſible Powers, which, they believ'd, will call every man to an account for his moſt ſecret Guilts. That's a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Inſtance of the Heathen Mariners in <hi>Jonah. Jon.</hi> 1. The Mariners there being affrighted at the terrible and unuſual Tempeſt. (which God, for <hi>Jonah</hi>'s ſake, ſent out into the Sea) reſolve among themſelves (<hi>v.</hi> 7.)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54305:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>to caſt Lots, that they might know for whoſe cauſe that Evil was upon them: Which intimates, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that the moſt ſecret faults were not unknown to the Omniſcient Being; and therefore reſolv'd to caſt Lots, which, they apprehended, did not fall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitouſly and by chance, but by Divine direction, and the guidance of an inviſible hand. So <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerves, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. <hi>ult. The lot is caſt into the lap; but the whole diſpoſing thereof is of the Lord.</hi> And though the Lot fell upon <hi>Jonah,</hi> who confeſt that he was a Fugitive Prophet, and that for his ſake the Sea was tempeſtuous, and that the only Expedient to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage its raging, was to caſt him over-board, which he bid them do: yet the men were afraid,
<note place="margin">Jon. 1.12.</note> being loth to contract the guilt of Murder, knowing that 'twas a cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſin, and that the voice of his Bloud would cry aloud, and plead againſt them before the inviſible Judge of the World; and therefore they tugg'd hard to get the Ship to Land, but all would not do, the Sea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more and more tempeſtuous; wherefore being forc'd to throw him over-board for their own ſafety, yet they did it with Cries and Prayers and earneſt Supplications to the great God, deprecating the guilt of Murder, and the cry of innocent Bloud, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>Wherefore they cried unto the Lord, and ſaid, We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, O Lord, we beſeech thee, let us not periſh for this man's life, and lay not upon us innocent bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if Natural Conſcience is ſo much affrighted at the thoughts, and hearing of Judgment, how much more,</p>
            <p n="2">2. An enlightned one; A Conſcience en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightn'd by the Light of Scripture, which gives the trueſt meaſures of ſin, and Divine wrath and venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. The Chriſtian has the beſt and trueſt account of the nature of ſin, and the ſad conſequents of it, is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54305:12"/>ſuppos'd to know and underſtand it beſt. And ſo he does, and therefore is ſufficiently affrighted at its ghaſtly looks, when he is under an apprehenſion of a ſpeedy approach to Judgment: Witneſs the cries and groans, the ſighs and lamentations of the ſick dying Sinner, whom you may hear, if you ſtep into his Chamber, as he lyes languiſhing upon his ſick Bed, lamenting and curſing his wicked life, and bewailing his ſins with all the aggravating inſtances of abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and deteſtation. Why, what's the matter? What ails the man? How comes it, that he is now ſo troubled at ſin, who before never fear'd it? Why, 'tis the Witneſs of God within him, whoſe mouth was ſtopt before, that thus ſpeaks. His Conſcience is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken'd, and does laſh and ſting him with a ſenſe of guilt, and the fiery vengeance, ſhews him what he has done, and whither he is a going, that he is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his trembling approach before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>That's the Second Evidence of the certainty of Judgment, <hi>viz. the Voice of Conſcience;</hi> The third is,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>The Voice of God's Juſtice,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that there ſhould be a future Judgment. They who will not be convinc'd by Scripture, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by this Argument, The conſideration of God's Juſtice, together with the State of Affairs, and things in this Life.</p>
            <p>They who have any ſenſe of Religion, and believe there is a God, muſt believe him to be juſt, that he is the juſt and righteous Governour of the World, a Lover of Juſtice, and will adminiſter Juſtice to his Creatures. Now, in regard we are not capable of an immediate converſe with God, who is a Spirit, and inviſible, he is pleas'd to converſe with us by men, by Creatures like our ſelves, and does appoint
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54305:12"/>ſome as his Vice-gerents, his Delegates and Subſtitutes here on Earth, to execute the Laws of Juſtice, and make an equal diſtribution of it, in giving rewards, and inflicting puniſhments, according to the nature and merit of the actions of men, and to render to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one his due.</p>
            <p>Now 'tis notorious, that Juſtice is not univerſally and impartially executed in this Life. The vertuous are not always rewarded, nor the vicious puniſhed, according to the different nature of their actions. Of which I could give you various Inſtances: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the Caſe of Perſecution. Good men, that fear God, are many times perſeucted for the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as the Martyrs in the <hi>Marian</hi> Days, and other Proteſtants in <hi>Christendom.</hi> Theſe were good, and yet receiv'd evil; they had not the reward of their Vertue here. What ſhould I ſpeak of that Cloud of Witneſſes, that noble Army of Martyrs mentioned in the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who had <hi>tryal of cruel mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſcourgings, yea moreover of bonds and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, were ſtoned, were ſawn aſunder, were tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, were ſlain with the ſword; wandred about in Sheep skins, and Goat skins, being destitute, afflicted, tormented; of whom the World was not worthy?</hi> On the other ſide, their Perſecutors fared well, though they did ſo ill; did not receive the recompence of their Vices, and wickedneſs, and cruelties, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies; had not their puniſhment in this Life, liv'd in pleaſure, and dy'd in peace, <hi>i. e.</hi> outward peace.</p>
            <p>And now where is the Juſtice of God, in reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vertue, and puniſhing Vice, if there is no future Audit of theſe matters, if theſe things eternally ſleep thus, if the perſecuted ſhall never be rewarded, and their Perſecutors never be puniſhed?</p>
            <p>But God is juſt, and will ſee Juſtice done, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54305:13"/>impartially executed. So the Apoſtle tells the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted Chriſtians. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6, 7. <hi>It is a righteous thing with God to recompence tribulation to them that trouble you: and to you who are troubled reſt with us, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven, with his mighty Angels.</hi> Again,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the times of confuſion, and licentiouſneſs, and rebellion, when <hi>there is no King in Iſrael,</hi> then <hi>every one does what ſeems good in his own eyes;</hi> Vice and wickedneſs walk bare-fac'd and uncontroul'd; and the plundering Thief, the bloudy Murderer, and Traytor goes perhaps to his Grave in peace, yea, with the Pompous Solemnities of a Royal Funeral.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yea, in Times of Peace, and the regular Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Juſtice, Vice, though it dare not walk ſo impudently, bare-fac'd and uncontroul'd, yet may lurk in Corners, and skulk up and down in ſecret, and eſcape the Magiſtrate's eye; the Thief, the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, the Traytor may be quick of Foot, and ſwift of Wing, and fly from Juſtice, and may never be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by it in this Life.</p>
            <p>Yea, even in Courts of Judicature 'tis impoſſible that Juſtice ſhould be univerſally and equally admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, (let none miſtake me, as if I deſign'd to aſperſe, or reflect on our Governours, and the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Judges of the Land, but I obſerve in general that) I ſay, 'tis impoſſible, even in Courts of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature, and the beſt upon Earth too, (where <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment runs down as waters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>and righteouſneſs as a mighty ſtream</hi>) that Juſtice ſhould be always equally diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For (not to ſpeak of the corruption of the Judge's heart, and the blinding of his eyes by Bribes (which <hi>turns Judgment into Gall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>and the fruit of righteouſneſs into Hemlock</hi>) which is not impoſſible, conſidering that he is but a man: I ſay, not to ſpeak of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54305:13"/>this, but) ſuppoſing the Judge to be as juſt as <hi>Job,</hi> (of whom God teſtifies, that there was none like him in the Earth, <hi>a perfect and upright man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>one that feared God, and eſchewed evil</hi>) one whoſe eyes cannot be blinded with Bribes, or prejudice, or partial favour, or malice; yet they may be blinded with untruth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on miſ-information. Some perjur'd Villain may deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately ſwear his Neighbour out of his Eſtate, or good Name, or Life. And the Judge nothwithſtanding is to proceed <hi>ſecundum allegata &amp; probata,</hi> according to the Evidence, whether true or falſe; for he ſees through the eyes of others: and ſo every one may not have Juſtice done him: Sometimes the guilty e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcapes, and receives not the demerit of his Crimes, is not dealt with according to the evil <hi>he hath done in his Body.</hi> On the other ſide, the innocent may fall a Sacrifice to miſtaken Juſtice, receive according to the ſuppoſed evil he hath not, and not according to the real good <hi>he hath done in his body:</hi> the Judge the mean while remaining really and invincibly ignorant of the truth upon miſ-information; and yet may be ſaid to do Juſtice; he does it intentionally and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally, though materially and by accident it proves o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. But that's reſerv'd to the ſerutiny of the ſupreme Judge, it falls under his cognizance, <hi>who ſearcheth the hearts, and tries the reins;</hi> who, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>will bring every work into Judgment;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>with every ſecret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The certainty of which Judgment is methinks ſufficiently evinc'd by the Obſervation of theſe things; that Juſtice is not, no nor cannot be univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally and impartially adminiſtred in this Life, that good men have not always the reward of their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, nor wicked men the recompence of their Vice
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54305:14"/>and wickedneſs: therefore, God being juſt, and the God of Juſtice, and the juſt Governour of the World, who is concern'd in the Affairs of Mortals, and ſits in the Seats of Judicature, and ſees and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords all that's done in his Book of remembrance, the great Regiſter of humane actions, there muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily come a Day, when all things ſhall be au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, and examined, and tryed before him, and all things ſet to rights, and a juſt Judgment paſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all, and every one receive (as 'tis worded in the Context) <hi>the things done in his body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good, or bad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much for the ſecond Particular, which I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to ſpeak to, <hi>viz.</hi> The certainty of a future Judgment. Come we now in the third Place, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire,</p>
            <p n="3">III. Into the ſeverity and dreadfulneſs of this Judgment, ſtyled here <hi>The Terrour of the Lord;</hi> it being the cauſe of Terrour, and that both to good and bad, and that both in this life, and that to come.</p>
            <p>In this Life, 'tis a Terrour even to good men, which keeps 'em in a holy awe, and cauſeth them to <hi>work with fear and trembling.</hi> They often look back towards the laſt things, and caſt an eye on the dreadful Tribunal of <hi>Jeſus Christ:</hi> which keeps 'em in a holy awe, fearing to offend him who ſhall be their Judge. It frights 'em from ſin, makes 'em afraid of the very appearance of evil: For though a Child of God acts from love, (which is the great and ingenuous Principle which moves him) yet that love is mixt with fear; 'tis the love of Sons, which is not a ſawcy, a malapert, a too bold and ſupercilious, a too familiar, wanton love; but a reverent, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive, humble love, a love that has an allay of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54305:14"/>fear, fear of diſpleaſing and offending their Father, whom it reſpects not only as good, and hating Vice, but as powerful, and able to puniſh it. In a word, 'tis not unmixed fear, which is the fear of Slaves, nor unmixed love, which is the love of Wantons, or at leaſt of Equals, who may love, but do not fear. In this holy awe and fear the thoughts of the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Judgment do eſpecially keep the Children of God (neither let it be thought Legal Preaching ſo to affirm) yea, their holy performances are mixt with fear; they <hi>work with fear and trembling;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> not ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's faithfulneſs, but their own, often thinking thus with themſelves, How ſhall I be able to hold out in the laſt hour, in my dying agonies? How ſhall I withſtand the Storms of Hell,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.16.</note> and <hi>quench the fiery Darts of</hi> the Devil? How ſhall I be able to appear before the great Tribunal? How ſhall I give up my Accounts there? Should God be ſtrict to mark what I have done amiſs, how ſhould I be able to <hi>ſtand in Judgment, or to anſwer him one of a thouſand?</hi> What if all theſe ſervices of mine ſhould be conſtrued then to be but hypocriſie and formality? What if God ſhould not accept my perſon, and owne my perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances? What if he ſhould fling back my ſervices as Dung, upon my Face, accounting it (as he did the Jew's) but <hi>as the cutting off of a Dog's neck;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 66.3.</note> 
               <hi>and the offering of Swines bloud in Sacrifice?</hi> What if my ſins ſhould appear hereafter unpardon'd, and my Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations uncancell'd? What though I am not far from the Kingdom of God, yet if for lack of one thing I ſhould fall ſhort of it? What if this cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs and baſe ſpiritedneſs, this worldly-minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and uncharitableneſs, this paſſion and peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, this ſtubbornneſs, this ſtiffneſs, and oppoſition, and diſobedience to my Governours, this deſire of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54305:15"/>revenge and heart-burning and animoſity; what if this, or any of theſe ſhould ruine all, and ſhut me out of Heaven? Lord, therefore, prays he, let me part with every thing that thou doſt hate, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace that which thou doſt love and command, that I may appear before thy <hi>Tribunal</hi> with courage and comfort!</p>
            <p>Thus the thoughts of Judgment ſtrike a holy awe and dread into the hearts of God's Children, and do ſucceſsfully affright 'em from ſin. It is thus a <hi>Terrour</hi> even to good men.</p>
            <p>And eſpecially 'tis a <hi>Terrour</hi> to wicked men, and impenitent Sinners, when under any affliction, or the apprehenſion of approaching Death. But after Death, eſpecially, 'twill be ſo; when the Judgment-Day is come, 'twill be <hi>Terrour</hi> with a Witneſs.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſuppos'd 'twill be a kind of Terrour to good men; which is gathered from that expreſſion in the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10. <hi>To be admir'd in all them that believe.</hi> Even in admiration it ſelf there is a kind of mixture of fear and Terrour, through an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verplus and overſlowing of expectation, and raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, exuberant wonder, as ſome are obſerv'd to weep for joy.</p>
            <p>But in wicked men all that's purely dreadful ſhall meet together.</p>
            <p>But more particularly, this dread and Terrour, which will fall upon wicked men, the Enemies of our Lord, ariſeth from theſe four things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſight of the Judge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The manner of his coming to Judgment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Accuſation of their own Conſciences.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Nature and Characters of the Judgment: Which will be,</p>
            <p n="1">1. An Univerſal, a General Judgment.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:54305:15"/>
            <p n="2">2. An exact, an accurate, and critical Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A juſt and righteous Judgment.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The final Judgment.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A Judgment that will ſentence to an eternal ſtate, either of happineſs or miſery.</p>
            <p>But perhaps ſome may be here diſſatisfied, being ready to demand, Whether none ſhall be ſentenc'd to an eternal ſtate till the laſt and general Judgment? What then ſhall become of departed Souls after Death, till the General Judgment? Shall they be kept in ſome <hi>Middle Place,</hi> in ſome <hi>Limbus Patrum,</hi> or <hi>Infantum?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer: As there is a General Judgment, at which the Body and Soul being re-united, ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and receive Sentence together; ſo there is a particular Judgment of the Soul by it ſelf, at its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from the Body. That the Souls of good men, immediately after Death, are carried to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Angels, to receive the Sentence of Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which ſhall be pronounced by Chriſt, who will place them in the Manſions of Glory, is moſt certain: as may be gathered from the Caſe of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus, Luke</hi> 16.22. compared with 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</p>
            <p>And I humbly conceive, (with ſubmiſſion) which is not unwarrantable by Scripture, (as is intimated in the Caſe of <hi>Dives, Luke</hi> 16.23.) that Chriſt Jeſus, the Judge of the World, by virtue of his Regal Office (which he doth now execute) as he ſends out his Angels, which are <hi>miniſtring Spirits,</hi> to carry ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Souls into Heaven, ſo he commiſſions his Angels too, to take the Souls of wicked men, immediately after their ſeparation, and deliver 'em to the Devil, that cruel Jaylor, the Keeper of the Infernal Priſon, who inſtantly draggs 'em away to Hell, there to be bound
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54305:16"/>(as 'tis ſaid of the evil Angels) <hi>in everlasting chains under darkneſs to the judgment of the great day;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 6.</note> and in the mean time to be tormented, and puniſhed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their capacity; and that in purſuance of the ancient Sentence, pronounced long ago; <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth not is condemn'd already,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 3.18, 36.</note> 
               <hi>and the wrath of God abideth on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having diſcours'd Doctrinally of that great Fundamental Point of Religion, the <hi>certainty of Judgment</hi> to come, a Day of <hi>Judgment</hi> after this Life, together with the dreadfulneſs of it, ſtyled here <hi>The Terrour of the Lord:</hi> It remains now</p>
            <p>IV. and Laſtly, that we make ſome improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it by Application.</p>
            <p>And here, firſt of all, I hope I need not uſe Saint <hi>Peter</hi>'s Apology to you (how needful ſoever 'tis amongſt others in the World) for the Lord's ſlackneſs, and delay in coming to Judgment; which he directs to thoſe Scoffers of the laſt times, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Knowing this firſt, that there ſhall come in the laſt days Scoffers, walking after their own luſts, and ſaying, Where is the promiſe of his coming? for ſince the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fell aſleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the Creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope there are no ſuch <hi>Scoffers</hi> here, though with ſorrow, and ſadneſs, and lamentation I might ſpeak it, and obſerve it, they abound too much in the World, yea in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> it ſelf, and this reformed Part of it; men of an Atheiſtical, ſhall I ſay, or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Chriſtian Spirit, who laugh and mock at the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of a <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> as a wild <hi>Chimaera,</hi> the idle Dream and fancy of a melancholy Preacher, the effect of an inquiſitive, contemplative Head, and the ſtrength of imagination; being ready to ſay, in the Words of theſe <hi>Scoffers</hi> here mentioned by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54305:16"/>Where is the promiſe of his coming?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> Where is the Promiſe, or Prophecy fulfill'd, that Chriſt ſhall come to judge the World? for ſince the death of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and the Patriarchs, and the Prophets, and Chriſt himſelf, who told the World of a Day of <hi>Judgment,</hi> the World continues as it was, no altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion appears; and 'tis like to continue ſo for ever.</p>
            <p>Now this mocking and ſcoffing and infidelity owes it ſelf, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> obſerves, partly to their Luſts, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their wilful ignorance, and inadvertency and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſideration. Which (in regard there are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the World that are ready to join Iſſue with theſe <hi>Scoffers</hi> here) I will take particular notice of, both to obviate their Atheiſtical Objections, and Anti-Chriſtian ſcoffs, and to antidote you againſt the infection of a contagious Air.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then, It owes it ſelf partly to their Vices and Luſts: <hi>[Scoffers, walking after their own luſts]</hi> Some men ſo long abandoning themſelves to Vice become Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, and deny God; for 'tis their intereſt there ſhould be none: and upon the ſame Grounds they become Anti-Chriſtian, and deny Chriſt; deny his Divinity and Authority and Veracity, his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Aſcenſion into Heaven, and his coming to Judgment: For 'tis their intereſt that he ſhould never come; whoſe coming will be ſo terrible to all his Enemies; 'twill be to the perdition of ungodly men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It owes it ſelf partly to their wilful ignorance, and inadvertency, and inconſideration, and that of three things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, God's Power and Providence, both in the Creation and deſtruction of the World.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The nature of God, and his meaſure and account of time.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:54305:17"/>
            <p>Thirdly, His patience and long-ſuffering.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God's Power and Providence, both in the Creation and deſtruction of the World, <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6, 7. <hi>For this they willingly are ignorant of, That by the Word of God the Heavens were of old, and the Earth ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Water, and in the Water; whereby the World that then was, being overflowed with Water, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed. But the Heavens and the Earth which are now, by the ſame Word, are kept in store, reſerved unto fire, againſt the Day of Judgment, and perdition of ungodly men.</hi> The ſumm and force of which Argument is briefly this: God made the World (for it could not make it ſelf) and having the power over it, did once deſtroy it, <hi>i. e.</hi> the face of it, with the things in it, by water: and he has the ſame power over it ſtill, and can deſtroy it (as he has told us he will) by fire. If he could do the former, he can as eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do the latter. <hi>Noah</hi> propheſied of the former, and it came to paſs; and the Prophets, yea the great Prophet, Chriſt himſelf, has propheſied of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and why ſhould we not believe it? To this I might add, that other Prophecies in Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt have been fulfill'd, particularly that concerning his coming in the Fleſh; and why ſhould we diſ-believe this of his coming to Judgment?</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Nature of God, and his Meaſure and Account of Time, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>Be not ignorant of this one thing, that one day is with the Lord as a thouſand years, and a thouſand years as one day, q. d.</hi> You think it a long time e're Chriſt come to Judgment; and therefore conclude he will never come, judging of the Lord by your ſelves, not underſtanding and conſidering his Divine Nature, which is Infinite, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe, Omniſcient and Eternal. He does not look upon things, and meaſure time as we do. He is not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54305:17"/>ſubject to ſucceſſion and mutation, as we are. He ſuffers no Flux of Time. There is no time paſt, or to come, with him. He does by one infinite Act of Intuition behold, and comprehend all things paſt and to come, as preſent: they all exiſt before him in one eternal <hi>Now.</hi> There is nothing, to ſpeak ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and properly, ſhort or long in his ſight, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of things. <hi>One day,</hi> which ſeems ſo ſhort with us, is with him as long as a <hi>thouſand years;</hi> and a <hi>thouſand years,</hi> which appear ſo long to us, are with him as ſhort <hi>as one day.</hi> Thoſe Periods of Time, that ſeem ſo long unto us, are with him but as a moment. So <hi>Moſes</hi> obſerves, <hi>Pſal</hi> 90.4. <hi>A thouſand years in thy ſight are but as yeſterday</hi> when it is paſt, (which is infinitely leſs than yeſterday when it was preſent) <hi>and as a Watch in the Night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This the Heathen were ſenſible of by the Light of Nature, aſcribing Immenſity to their Gods: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſays <hi>Pythagoras;</hi> There is nothing long with the Gods. And Divine <hi>Plutarch,</hi> ſpeaking of the late vengeance of the Deity, obſerves, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— All the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terval of humane life, is to the Gods nothing.</p>
            <p>This, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> obſerves, theſe Scoffers are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ignorant of, at leaſt inconſiderate; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore talk at ſuch a mad and ſenſleſs rate, and give way to, and indulge their Atheiſm and infidelity.</p>
            <p>And againſt this ignorance and inconſideration of the Nature of God, and his meaſure and account of Time, he cautions even the Friends of Chriſt, that they might not be diſcouraged with the thoughts of the <hi>Lord's ſlackneſs</hi> in coming to <hi>Judgment;</hi> or be tempted to entertain an Atheiſtical Anti-Chriſtian O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that he will never come, and ſo laugh, and mock at the Doctrine with theſe Scoffers here: and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54305:18"/>therefore he greets them with an endearing compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation <hi>[Beloved]</hi> which is an evidence that he ſpeaks to the Saints. <hi>But (Beloved) be not ignorant of this one thing (of which theſe</hi> Scoffers <hi>are wilfully ignorant</hi> and inconſiderate) <hi>that one day,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Scoffing and Infidelity owes it ſelf to their wilful ignorance and inconſideration of God's <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>long-ſuffering, v.</hi> 9. <hi>The Lord is not ſlack concerning his promiſe, (as ſome men count ſlackneſs) but is long-ſuffering to us-ward, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance. The Lord is not ſlack, as ſome men count ſlackneſs; i. e.</hi> as if he had chang'd his purpoſe, or broke his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, or were unwilling or unable to keep it, and fulfil it. He is not ſlack that ſtays long, but that ſtays beyond his appointed time, or that comes not at all. The Lord will not defer his coming to Judgment one moment beyond his appointed time. <hi>He that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry; i. e.</hi> beyond his own appointment. 'Tis not then becauſe he has forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his promiſe, or cannot keep it, or has over-ſlipt his appointed time, that he deferrs coming to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but out of infinite compaſſion and kindneſs to Sinners, being <hi>long-ſuffering, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance.</hi> Which theſe ungrateful Wretches are not ſenſible of, and therefore ſcoff and mock, kick and ſpurn at the Divine Bowels, abuſe that clemency which keeps 'em out of Hell, trample upon that patience which bears with their follies, and waits for their repentance, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe that love, and goodneſs which ſuſpends the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful vengeance. How paſſionately does the Apoſtle expoſtulate with ſuch as theſe! <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Deſpiſeſt thou the riches of his Goodneſs, and forbearance, and long-ſuffering, not knowing that the Goodneſs of God leadeth thee to repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:54305:18"/>
            <p>O that my Voice could this Day reach the ears, and pierce the heart of every ſcoffing Atheiſt, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, blaſpheming Sinner in this Kingdom! I would be bold to ask him ſeriouſly, Doſt thou think, O man! that the God that made thee, is not able to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thee? that he that created and preſerves thee, cannot judge thee? that he that governs and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds the World, is not able to deal with ſuch a weak, ſilly Creature as thou art? that he, in whom thou doſt <hi>live, and move, and haſt thy Being,</hi> is not able to deſtroy thee, and execute vengeance on thee? and therefore doſt dare him to his face, and bid him do his worſt againſt thee, and accelerate the ſlow-pac'd vengeance, laughing and mocking at the Divine threatnings, and the Doctrine of the future Judgment, as a thing which thou doſt not fear, and ſhalt never feel, ſporting with Hell and the Devil, bidding him take and rot and ſink thee, laughing at the Great Judge, and bidding him damn thee if he can; what elſe is the meaning of thoſe direful Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, thoſe horrid <hi>God-damn-me</hi>-Execrations, which pollute the Air, and wound the ears of God and men? I do not think that theſe men ſeriouſly deſire damnation, but out of a daring bravery, mock and deride God himſelf, and affront him to his face, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the World, that they do not fear him, nor his threatnings, nor all the powers of Hell, which he can ſet againſt them; that they are ſo little afraid of his damning power, that they will damn themſelves in a frolick, or bid him damn 'em if he can, and haſten his threatned Judgment.</p>
            <p>A very ill and ungrateful uſe of his patience and long-ſuffering! But 'tis ſuch as the Wiſe man ſpake of, and obſerv'd long ago, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.11. <hi>Becauſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence against an evil work is not executed ſpeedily, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54305:19"/>the heart of the ſons of men is fully ſet in them to do evil:</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> here intimates, and ſadly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, and bewails in this his paſſionate Expoſtulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Deſpiſeſt thou the riches of his Goodneſs,</hi> &amp;c. But hear, O deſpiſing, ſcoffing, ungrateful man! Hear what follows, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>After thy hardneſs, and impenitent heart thou treaſureſt up unto thy ſelf wrath against the day of wrath, and revelation of the righteous Judgment of God,</hi> who will render to every one according to his deeds. For though the Lord is <hi>long ſuffering,</hi> yet he will not be <hi>ever-ſuffering.</hi> But the day of the Lord will come, as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> obſerves, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. and it will come ſpeedily, <hi>as a Thief in the Night,</hi> unlookt for, and ſo ſurprize: or as 'tis worded, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>The day of the Lord ſo cometh, as a Thief in the night, for when they ſhall ſay, Peace and ſafety, then ſudden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction cometh upon them, as travail upon a Woman with Child, and they ſhall not eſcape.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, This Doctrine of the certainty, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, and dreadfulneſs of the future Judgment may ſerve to awaken ſecure Sinners out of their ſinful and dangerous ſecurity.</p>
            <p>As there are ſome that Atheiſtically ſcoff at Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſo there are others that are ſufficiently careleſs of it; do not ſpeak, but act againſt it; who live vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious lives, and are led by their paſſions and appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, and are regardleſs of the World to come, and ſtupidly and ſecurely ſinful. They are perhaps more carnal and ſenſual than the former, though not ſo Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolical. If there are any ſuch here, let me ſeriouſly ask them, Sirs! Do you believe the Bible to be true? Do you believe the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith? that there is a God that made the World, and governs it, that you have immortal Spirits within you, that are capable of endleſs happineſs or miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54305:19"/>that you muſt dye, and come to Judgment, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt, who ſhall come from Heaven to judge the quick and the dead? Do you believe all this? You'll readily anſwer, Yes that we do, God forbid we ſhould be Unbelievers, we can ſay our <hi>Creed</hi> as ſincerely and devoutly as the beſt. Can you ſo? What! and live in ſuch manifeſt contrariety and oppoſition to what you believe, and the terms of ſalvation, as if all this were falſe, as if all were cheat and impoſture, as if the Goſpel were a Fable, or an idle Romance! For God's ſake, Sirs! be ſerious, and conſider, and do not ſuffer your ſelves ſo tamely to be impos'd upon, and baffled by your Spiritual Enemies, thoſe that hate you, and will laugh at your folly, and triumph over your miſery; Do not live the reverſe of your Reaſon and Religion too, and contradict your Faith and Perſwaſion, and ſuffer your ſelves to be fool'd out of that eternal happineſs, which you ſay you hope for, and loſe the beſt and greateſt intereſt, which is more valuable than all the Treaſures and inſtances of happineſs in this World, which you muſt ſhortly leave, and dye from, when nothing here below, neither Riches, nor Friends can help you, but only an effectual ſaving intereſt in the Judge of the World:
<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 1.7, 8.</note> who will ſhortly <hi>be revealed from Heaven with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vengeance on them that know not God, and that do not obey his Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that I could make ſome ſecure Sinner here to tremble,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.14.</note> and effectually warn him to <hi>flee from the wrath to come! Awake, thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from the dead, and Christ ſhall give thee light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It exhorts us to Holineſs. And indeed this Doctrine is a powerful diſſwaſive from Vice, and perſwaſive to Vertue: a diſſwaſive from Vice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54305:20"/>it will be certainly and ſeverely puniſhed; a perſwaſive to Vertue, becauſe it will be certainly, and amply rewarded.</p>
            <p>I doubt not, but there are ſome that are very indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, as to the State of happineſs in the other World; for which they are not greatly concern'd, but could be content to part with it, provided they might not be miſerable; they could be content that their Bodies and Souls too ſhould ſleep eternally. They could be content perhaps not to be rewarded in Heaven, ſo that they might not be puniſhed in Hell. But know (Chriſtian!) that there is no <hi>medium</hi> here. If we are not rewarded, we ſhall certainly be puniſhed; if we are not happy, we muſt be miſerable. If we do not go to Heaven, we muſt to Hell. If we have not the enjoyment of God, we muſt have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Devils for ever. So that holineſs is indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably neceſſary, not only to intitle us to Heaven, but to keep us out of Hell. And there is no greater, or more forcible Argument to perſwade to holineſs, than this of <hi>Judgment to come.</hi> This is the great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument the Wiſe man uſeth to perſwade both to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative and poſitive holineſs. Thus, in the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of his <hi>Eccleſiastes, ver.</hi> 9. he does tacitly exhort to nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive holineſs; <hi>i. e.</hi> he does by a ſharp and keen, but pleaſant Irony diſſwade from Vice, and youthful Luſts, and ſinful Pleaſures, <hi>Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth, and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thine heart, and in the ſight of thine eyes:</hi> there follows a terrible <hi>But,</hi> which is like the Damp to the Candle, or the Death's Head to the Egyptian Feaſts, a Cooler to the heat of Luſt, and, like <hi>Belſhazzer</hi>'s hand upon the Wall, daſheth all that mirth and jollity: <hi>But know thou, that for all theſe things God will bring thee into Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:54305:20"/>
            <p>And <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 13. he exhorts to poſitive ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs (not excluding negative) <hi>i. e.</hi> to the practice of Vertue, and doing good: <hi>Fear God, and keep his Commandments; for this is the whole Duty of man.</hi> And this he preſſeth by the ſame Argument, the great Motive of <hi>Judgment to come, ver.</hi> 14. <hi>For God ſhall bring every work into Judgment, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the great beaten Argument that both the Prophets and Apoſtles are frequently upon, and ſpreading before the eyes of men. Moſt of the weighty Exhortations in Scripture (like the Scales upon the Beam) are faſtned upon this: therefore work, walk, run, ſtrive, deny your ſelves, <hi>be ſtedfaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, foraſmuch as you know that your labour is not in vain in the Lord.</hi> 'Tis the great Argument both to Active and Paſſive Obedience. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> obſerves it to be ſo, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8. <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith: Henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of righteouſneſs, which the Lord the righteous Judge ſhall give me at that day:</hi> It follows, <hi>and not to me only, but to all them alſo that love his appearing.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle does by this Argument ſupport the Spirits of thoſe who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd for the name of Chriſt, whoſe invincible pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and faith in perſecution and tribulation he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauds and glories in, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.14. aſſuring them <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>It is a righteous thing with God to recompence tribulation to them that trouble you; and to you who are troubled rest with us, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8. exhorts to patience under tribulation by this Argument, <hi>Be patient therefore, Brethren, unto the coming of the Lord:</hi> which he obſerves will be as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54305:21"/>ſure as the joyful Harveſt after Seed-time, for which the Huſbandman waits with patience: <hi>Behold, the Husbandman waiteth for the precious fruit of the Earth, and hath long patience for it, until he receive the early and latter rain: Be ye alſo patient; ſtabliſh your hearts, for the coming of the Lord draweth nigh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the great Pillar and Under-prop to ſupport the Spirits of men both in doing and ſuffering the Will of God. Alas! It would be comfortleſs labour, could we not look over the Burden to the Reward; unpleaſant Work, where there is no expectation of Wages; dull and heavy and diſcouraging Service, where there is no hope of recompence, or of any advantage.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, Vertue is in it ſelf lovely, and ſome ſay its own reward. But God is not content that it ſhould be ſo; but propounds a real Reward as the End of Vertue: which he allows us to regard, and look to, as our great encouragement to all vertuous Actions.</p>
            <p>'Tis recorded as an Act of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Faith, and a Point of his Praiſe, that he had an eye <hi>to the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of reward, Heb.</hi> 11.26.</p>
            <p>'Tis not unworthy of a Chriſtian, as if he were to be thought a Mercenary to do this. 'Tis true indeed a Chriſtian muſt not have <hi>amorem mercenarium,</hi> but he may have <hi>amorem mercedis;</hi> though not a merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary love, yet a love of the reward. Though he may not ultimately eye his own reward, yet he may in a ſecondary and ſubſervient manner. God's Glory muſt be our chief and ultimate, but our own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt may be our ſecondary and ſubſervient End. God will have none of his Servants to ſerve him for nought: they <hi>ſhall in no wiſe loſe their reward:</hi> which he allows us to look to with <hi>Moſes</hi> here, who
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54305:21"/>had <hi>reſpect unto the recompence of reward,</hi> which ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported him under doing and ſuffering for God, <hi>v.</hi> 25, 26. <hi>chuſing rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeming the reproach of Chriſt greater riches than the treaſures of Egypt:</hi> the reaſon of which eminent acts of ſelf-denial and reſignation is aſſign'd in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Words, <hi>For he had reſpect unto the recompence of reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as it ſupported him, ſo it has and does others too. This ſupported S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> in the mouth of the roaring Roman Lyon
<note n="*" place="margin">Nero.</note>. This ſupported S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Stephen</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Showre of Stones; He lookt to the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of reward, and ſaw it in his Redeemer's hand;
<note place="margin">Acts 7.55, 56.</note> 
               <hi>the Heavens were open'd</hi> to him, <hi>and he ſaw Jeſus ſtanding at the right hand of God.</hi> This ſupported the Martyrs under their Fiery Tryals; whilſt their Bodies were melting at the Stake, their Souls were inflam'd with holy ardours, and fortified with invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible courage, their Faith giving 'em a proſpect of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſtanding at the right hand of God,</hi> not with fading Garlands, but immarceſſible Crowns of Glory in his hand, to ſet upon their triumphant heads.</p>
            <p>Indeed without this, how ſoon would the Spirits faint in the beſt Chriſtian! In all the Inſtances of Mortification, and Self-denial, and Suffering, and Perſecution for Religion, could he not look to the recompence of reward, what diſcouragement would he labour under! He might thus argue with himſelf: What do I do! I am a Lover of Religion, and am ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for it; I deny my ſelf in point of the profits and pleaſures of the World, which others wallow in to ſatiety; I do good, and receive evil; am vexed and troubled and perſecuted in this World, whilſt others are at reſt. And to what end is all this? What!
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54305:22"/>that I ſhould live like a Fool, and dye like a Beaſt? And ſurely ſo it would be, were there no future re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for him to eye, and have reſpect to. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s Hypotheſis is a Great Truth, and the Conſequence natural, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19. <hi>If in this life only we have hope in Chriſt, we are of ll men moſt miſerable.</hi> Only there is a comfortable <hi>But</hi> which turns the Scales, converts the Hypothetick into a Categorical Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the next Words: <hi>But now is Chriſt riſen from the dead, and become the firſt-fruits of them that ſlept;</hi> who ſhall riſe with him too, and appear at Judgment, <hi>the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The thoughts of which, as it ſtrikes unſpeakable Terrour into ill men, (perhaps here, as well as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after) ſo it comforts and refreſheth, ſtrangely enli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and animates, invigorates and encourages good men to, and in all the Inſtances of their Duty, both in doing and ſuffering. What will they ſtick at? What difficulties dare they not encounter with? What Obſtacles can they not remove, or break through? What Lyon in the way ſhall diſcourage them, or turn them back? What ſhall divert them from purſuing ſuch great and ſure rewards, which are before their eyes, which they ſhall one day cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly receive? What ſhall turn <hi>them</hi> out of the way of the Lord, whoſe eyes are fixed on this Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Object? Shall the Enchantments or bewitching Charms of ſinful Pleaſures allure, or the thundering Peals of Perſecution fright 'em thence? May not ſuch make S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s triumphant Challenge, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35. <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt? Shall tribulation, or distreſs, or perſecution, or famine, or nakedneſs, or peril, or ſword, or any other Creature whatſoever? Nay, in all theſe things we are more than Conquerours through him that loved us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:54305:22"/>
            <p>Go on then (Chriſtian!) with courage and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and let thine eye be ever fixed on this Glorious Object, look to the recompence of reward, have an eye to the Glories that <hi>are within the Veil,</hi> act Faith upon the things unſeen, keep a conſtant eye upon the <hi>Judge</hi> of the World, and the great <hi>Tribunal,</hi> and let thy Meditations on it be frequent, and deep, and ſerious: and then leave the way of the Lord, if thou canſt; then let the pleaſures of ſin bewitch thee, and turn thee aſide, if they can, <hi>like a broken Bow;</hi> then leave the narrow, and walk in the broad way that leads to deſtruction, then turn thy face (which now looks Heaven-ward) to the Regions of darkneſs, if thou canſt; then apoſtatize from thy Religion, and renounce Chriſtianity, bid adieu to the Communion of Saints, and aſſociate with the blacker Spirits, and the Cabal of Hell, if thou canſt; then let the World, the Fleſh and the Devil tempt thee to evil, ſeduce, conquer and triumph over thee, if they can; then ſhrink and faint, hide thy head and deny thy <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> in the Storms of Perſecution, thoſe bloudy Showres, and prove a baſe, cowardly Deſerter, if thou canſt; then let thoſe fiercer, ruder Winds of Hell, thoſe turbulent <hi>Euroclydons,</hi> ſhipwrack thy Faith, if they can: there is no danger ſurely if thy Anchor-hold be <hi>ſure and stedfaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.19.</note> 
               <hi>faſtned within the Veil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all the Inſtances of Duty, in all the Turns of Providence, in all the Occurrences of humane Life, in all the Temptations either of the <hi>World,</hi> or the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> or the <hi>Devil,</hi> always remember there is a Day of Judgment coming, when wicked men ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and good men ſhall be rewarded: then thou ſhalt have thy reward, though thou tarrieſt long for it; a reward that will abundantly compenſate all
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54305:23"/>thy trouble, all thy labour, all thy love, all thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and ſufferings for thy Lord and Maſter; a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that will be infinitely ſatisfactory and Glorious, that infinitely exceeds all the Honours and Glories and Names of Happineſs in this lower World: which Earthly Crowns and Scepters cannot purchaſe, nor the United Power of Earth, and Hell rob or deprive thee of; which Devils will envy thee, and wicked men wiſh for, as well as be amazed at, who ſhall ſtand trembling at the dreadful Barr,
<note place="margin">Wiſd. 5.1, &amp;c.</note> whilſt thou art exulting, on the Throne; who will ſtand aſhamed in their poverty and nakedneſs, whilſt thy brighter Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Royal Robes are putting on, beholding with horrour what is <hi>done to the man whom the King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth to honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O terrible, and yet O comfortable glorious Day! A Day indeed of gloomineſs and blackneſs, of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and aſtoniſhment, a Day of <hi>Terrour</hi> and the blackeſt grief, and the deepeſt ſorrow to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but a Day of comfort and joy, a Day of mirth and gladneſs to the Friends of Chriſt! A Day of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> calls it, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. <hi>When the time of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord.</hi> 'Twill be truly a time of <hi>refreſhing; refreſhing</hi> to the <hi>weary,</hi> tired Traveller, when he comes to ſit down at reſt; the Chriſtian that was burden'd, and <hi>weary, and heavy-laden</hi> with corruption and ſin, who ſhall then have a true, intire and perfect reſt; <hi>refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to the buffetted, tempted, afflicted Saint; <hi>refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to the weather-beaten,
<note place="margin">Cant. 1.6. Luke 21.28.</note> 
               <hi>ſun-burn'd</hi> afflicted Church of Chriſt. A Day of Redemption, as our Saviour ſtyles it, full and compleat Redemption, Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from all ſin and temptation and miſery; full Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from ſorrow and tears and ſuffering, when ſorrow ſhall be no more, and all tears ſhall be wip'd
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54305:23"/>away. So the Spirit aſſures us in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> ſpeaking of the Immunities of that Bleſſed State, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.4. <hi>And God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes: and there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow, nor crying, neither ſhall there be any more pain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly and Laſtly, Is there ſuch infallible cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Judgment to come? Is there a Day of Judgment coming, when we muſt all appear before Jeſus Chriſt, the Judge both of the quick and dead? O then let us make preparation for it, (which it concerns us all to do) and that ſpeedily; and here I might give you theſe following Directions, which I ſhall but name.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Get your Accounts ready. Look into your ſelves, and examine your ſtate; how it ſtands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God, and your Souls, that you may not be ſurpriz'd, when you ſhall be ſummon'd to <hi>appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judgment-Seat of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Do nothing now which you dare not account for then, which you would not then hear of.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Buy, and put on your Wedding-Garments,
<note place="margin">Rev. 3.17. Mat. 22.11, 12. — 25.1, &amp;c.</note> and get your <hi>Lamps trim'd</hi> and furniſh'd with <hi>Oil</hi> to meet the <hi>Bridegroom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Make Chriſt, who is the <hi>Judge,</hi> your <hi>Friend.</hi> And that muſt be done,</p>
            <p>Firſt, By keeping his Commandments, eſpecially thoſe which are more peculiarly his, thoſe Laws which have their immediate Inſtitution and Sanction in the Goſpel, particularly that of <hi>the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper.</hi> Which they that deſpiſe, and contemn, and neglect, may ſadly remember and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that 'tis <hi>his Ordinance</hi> who will be their <hi>Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, By obliging his Friends. And how that is to be done, he himſelf intimates, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.35, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:54305:24"/>
            <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.13.</note> Be always upon your Watch.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Add to Watching Prayer. This is our Lord's Advice, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Mark</hi> 13.33. <hi>Take ye heed, watch and pray, for ye know not when the time is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will conclude all with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi>'s Exhortation, which he makes from this very Doctrine of the final Judgment, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11, 12. <hi>Seeing then that all theſe things ſhall be diſſolved, (i. e.</hi> ſeeing that this World, and all things here below, ſhall have an End, and Chriſt ſhall come to Judgment) <hi>what manner of perſons ought ye to be in all holy converſation and godlineſs! Looking for, and hasting unto the coming of the day of God—</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>Wherefore (Beloved) ſeeing that ye look for ſuch things, be diligent, that ye may be found of him in peace, without ſpot, and blameleſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
